## Robert C. Foster

CONTACT Information Office 03-132-345 Los Alamos National Laboratory www.robertcfoster.com Phone: (505) 667-6055 Work: rcfoster@lanl.gov Personal: rcfoster@gmail.com

Statistician with a strong applied background in the sciences and engineering, skilled communicator, and excellent team member.

RESEARCH INTERESTS Applied statistical methods with a focus on science and engineering applications, Bayesian and empirical Bayesian methods, statistical programming, uncertainty quantification, and quantum computation.

## EDUCATION

#### Ph.D. in Statistics

## Iowa State University, Ames, IA, October 2016

- Thesis title: Topics in Empirical Bayesian Analysis
- Adviser: Mark S. Kaiser
- 3.65 GPA
- My dissertation focuses on comparing and contrasting the ways that the uncertainty introduced into empirical Bayesian methods from double use of the data (once for estimation of the hyperparameters, once in the resulting Bayesian analysis) has been accounted for. Several of these disparate methods are combined into one consistent framework. A new method is proposed for deriving empirical Bayesian intervals for means of natural exponential families with quadratic variance functions based on a modified method of Carl Morris.

#### M.S. in Statistics

### Iowa State University, Ames, IA, December 2010

- Thesis title: Simulation Analysis of a Bayesian Test Plan for Sequential Data from a Homogeneous Poisson Process
- Adviser: Alyson Wilson
- 3.65 GPA
- My thesis analyzes a Bayesian method for obtaining a sequential test plan
  based on a specific type of data and determines how the estimated test
  plan is affected by choice of the prior distribution on the parameters. The
  performance of the estimated test plan under model misspecification is
  also investigated.

#### **B.S.** in Mathematics and Statistics

Oklahoma State University, Stillwater, OK, May 2007

- Summa cum laude
- Minor in Computer Science
- 3.948 GPA
- Honors college degree

# RESEARCH EXPERIENCE

# Los Alamos National Laboratory, Los Alamos, NM

CCS-6, Statistical Sciences group

Postdoctoral Researcher, Oct. 2016 - Present

Research topics include sources of uncertainty for computation techniques
that lie "Beyond Moore's Law" and the statistical properties of resulting
errors from propagation of BML uncertainties, simulation of microstructures from samples of additively manufactured materials, and applications
of quantum computing in statistics.

# Iowa State University, Ames, IA

Department of statistics

Research Assistant, 2007-2010

• Consulted with various departments and research groups at Iowa State University, including animal science and the agriculture experiment station (AES).

# TEACHING EXPERIENCE

#### Iowa State University, Ames, IA USA

Department of Statistics

Instructor

## August 2010 to May 2016

- Principles of Statistics: Fall 2010, Spring 2011, Summer 2011, Fall 2011, Spring 2012, Summer 2012
- Probability and Statistics for Computer Science: Fall 2012, Spring 2013, Fall 2013, Spring 2014
- Engineering Statistics: Fall 2014
- Probability and Statistical Inference for Engineers: Spring 2015, Spring 2016

# PUBLICATIONS IN PREPARATION

Foster, R., Vander Wiel, S., Livescu, V., and Bronkhorst, C., 'Towards Recreation of Microstructure of Spatially Varying Materials from Orthogonal Sections, Computational Materials Science (Manuscript)

Foster, R., Weaver, B. and Gattiker, J., 'Quantum Computing in Statistics using the D-Wave Quantum Annealer," *The American Statistician* (In Preparation)

Foster, R., Weaver, B. and Gattiker, J. "Combining Observational and Computational Uncertainty in Stochastic Emulators," (In Preparation)

TECHNICAL REPORTS Abendroth, Lori; Marlay, Stephanie; Myers, Anthony J.W.; Elmore, Roger W.; and Foster, Robert C., "Regional Corn Planting Date Recommendations for Iowa" (2010). Iowa State Research Farm Progress Reports. 410.

INVITED TALKS

Towards Recreation of Microstructure in Additively Manufactured Materials, International Conference on Plasticity, Jan. 2018; Albuquerque ASA spring meeting, Apr. 2018

Professional Membership

• American Statistical Association

Computing Expertise Statistical Software: R, JMP, SAS, Matlab Programming Languages: Python, Java, C

Applications: TEX, LATEX, BIBTEX, Microsoft Office Operating Systems: Microsoft Windows, macOS, Unix